גוט טוב, Gut Tov, today's דף Daf is, we're going to say
it's
134, we start on קל"ג עמוד ב', Kuf Lamed Gimmel Amud Bais,
but we will see, I think we can get back to being
where we were, and we pick up with
the משנה. Mishna. Not a somewhat new subject, obviously it's all within
the larger theme here about somebody dying and being either bequeathing his
property, and recently we discussed cases where a person can identify which
son is the בכור, Bechor, and based on the פסוק Pasuk of
כי את הבכור בן השנואה יכיר, Ki Es Habechor Ben Hasnuah Yakir,
he must recognize who the בכור Bechor is. So even if somebody
is presumed to be a younger child, we פסקן Pasken according to
the גמרא Gemara that you recognize to say that this one is
the בכור. Bechor. Now this משנה, Mishna, in a similar vein, says
the following.
I think I jumped ahead. That's the משנה Mishna coming up after
this משנה, Mishna, the contrast of בכור. Bechor. This משנה Mishna is
still within this context of the redistributing the property and the רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rabbi Yochanan Ben Broka. So we learned from רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan Ben Broka you can even redistribute the
property and assign different percentages or whatever between the יורשים, Yorshim, and
חכמים Chachamim say you can't do it as a ירושה, Yerusha, but
you could do it as a מתנה. Matana. So this משנה Mishna
then says the following: הכותב את נכסיו לאחרים. Hakosev Es Nechasav Leachairim.
So let's say you basically did this, you wrote out a will
and you donated your property, you gave it to all other people,
not your family, והניח את בניו, Vehiniach Es Banav, and you left
your kids, you disinherited, you empty-handed by writing all your property away
to somebody else, donating it all to the cancer society. מה שעשה
עשוי, Ma Sheasa Asuy, what is done is done, אלא אין חכמים
נוחה הימנו, Ella Ein Chachamim Nocha Hemenno, clearly it's effective, but the
rabbis are not happy with you to completely disinherit your kids. Now
this is ironic because we just got through saying how, and we
haven't even fully explored it, but how the rabbis made it possible
for somebody to redistribute their property. As long as you use the
word מתנה, Matana, you even say ירושה Yerusha at the beginning and
ירושה Yerusha at the end, if you somewhere in there have a
word of מתנה Matana we're going to interpret it as a gift
to give you the power to distribute your property as you see
fit. Nevertheless, it seems to be that this משנה Mishna is pushing
back on this and is sort of saying, one way to sort
of read this is if you completely abandon your children that's not
appropriate. There could be an abuse of this. To a certain degree,
to distribute your property, but you should also leave behind something for
your children. That would seem to be the way if you wanted
to read those two in balance. The other way to read them
would just be really different
voices, one voice that's more pragmatic and wants to give people the
ability and develops this idea about מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shechiv Meira.
מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira is an extreme expression of that.
You don't even have to do a normal קניין, Kinyan, it's just
a verbal bequest. It really shows the rabbis wanted to give a
person a power to distribute the property, and maybe there's a contrary
voice that
says at the same time we gave a person all this power,
we're really not happy with this, which would be strange, but it
would be possible, interesting, for the הלכה Halacha to try to embrace
both of those. But if you wanted to reconcile those two approaches,
you could say that this is talking about when
he completely disinherits the kids, completely doesn't leave them anything. אלא אין
חכמים נוחה הימנו. Ella Ein Chachamim Nocha Hemenno. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel אמר, Amar, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel says, אם לא היו בניו נוהגים כשורה זכור לטוב. Im
Lo Hayu Banav Nohagim Kashura Zachur Latov. If his children were not
acting properly then this person should be remembered for good, meaning that
actually the opposite, we're not exactly quite happy with him because I
use this, the threat of disinheriting or the fact of disinheriting as
a way of actually ensuring that the property goes to the person
who deserves it. Now again, this actually is funny
because it can be seen as evoking, we've spoken about this before,
that value in the תורה Torah that's in the narratives of the
תורה Torah but not in the הלכות Halachos or the מצוות Mitzvos
of the תורה, Torah, which is that the בכור Bechor portion, the
בכור Bechor in the תורה Torah is not the firstborn, the one
who inherits the status and
the family, head of the family sort of role in the whatever,
is the one who's deserving. From all the stories from the beginning
of the תורה, Torah, from קין Kayin and
הבל Hevel to אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham, Yitzchak, and Yaakov, the entire
Jewish nation, בני בכורי ישראל, Bni Bechori Yisrael, is the בכור Bechor
is the deserving child, the chosen one, not the one who happens
to be the firstborn. Except then the הלכה Halacha in the תורה
Torah is
לא יוכל לבכר את בן האהובה על פני בן השנואה הבכור. Lo
Yuchal Levaker Es Ben Ha'ahuva Al Pnei Ben Hasnuah Habechor. So actually
here though,
other than until now we've pointed out that the rabbis created a
sort of a mechanism for effectively doing that
by redistributing the property in מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira and
so on. Here רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel is
giving explicit articulation to that value. The people, the ones that should
get the property are the people who are deserving of it. And
if the kids aren't deserving, then the property should go to the
deserving. Now that's actually to even deserving others over your undeserving children.
But he actually says that actually would be appropriate. So let's take
a look at, yes, is there any parallel? Yesterday we learned that
you can sort of disinherit the wife, you know, if you do
it in the right way. Is there any pushback kind of about
this? Well, this is the pushback, meaning we've given you the mechanism,
we've given you the mechanism to effectively disinherit your sons through a
מתנה matana or through a, you know, an actual מתנה matana or
a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera and even if you use
the word מתנה matana together with the word ירושה yerusha we're going
to interpret it that way. So we've actually created not only, you
know, extra mechanisms to let you do it and now we're sort
of pushing back on that. Right. So this all mentions the sons,
it doesn't mention your wife. Oh, oh, oh, yeah, it's a good
point. All right, I don't know, but anyway here it's, you know,
there, right, it's a different issue, there it's like undermining the Rabbinic
כתובה ketubah concept that we dealt with yesterday which was meant to
protect the woman, this is undermining like biblical inheritance, but yeah, okay.
איבעיא להו, Iba'ia lehu, but as I hear the point. Okay, they
raise the question: מי פליגי רבנן עליה דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל או
לא? Mi peligi rabanan aleih de-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel o lo? What's
about this scenario as Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel clarifying the רבנן? Rabanan?
By the way, we don't like it when you disinherit your sons
except in this case and maybe the Rabbis agree with that sentiment?
Or do the Rabbis say no, even if the sons are acting
inappropriately you should not disinherit them? So תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear. דיוסף בן יועזר, Diyosef ben Yoezer, היה לו בן, haya
lo ben, Yosef ben Yoezer had a son, שלא היה נוהג כשורה,
shelo haya noheg keshura, he wasn't acting appropriately, that's the same phrase
in the Mishna, נוהג כשורה, noheg keshura, okay, like going down the,
like it's like staying on the straight and narrow, like like walking
the line, right? It's from כשר. kasher.
Right, it's שורה. shura. Right, right, okay, he's like not walking down
the straight and narrow, right, he's not toeing the line, okay. הוה
ליה עליתא דדינרי. Hava lei alita de-dinarei. He had an עליתא alita
of dinarin. Now עליתא alita usually means an attic-full, but that, which
would obviously be an exaggeration, but the Gemara later makes it sound
like it's an accurate measure. So Tosafos says עליתא alita here means
like a basketful, not a, not an attic-full. Okay, anyway, so he
had, we'll read it that way, a basketful of gold dinarei. קם
אקדשה, Kam akdeshei, and this was his like apparently his whole property,
and he went and he sanctified it to the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash to keep it out of the hands of his son. Now
by the way, what's also interesting about this is, you know, I
was reading the Mishna because I was trying to make it balance
with other things we've talked, completely disinherit the son. There's nothing about
this story that says that this represented his entire wealth, right, or,
you know, that he didn't get money afterwards. You might, you know,
the sense is that maybe it means that, you know, he took
the son, a major part of the son's inheritance and gave it
to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So that's interesting as well, like
is the criticism in the Mishna applied only to a person who
completely disinherits his, his children or even like majorly disinherits? All right,
so this story you don't get the sense that it was a
complete disinheritance. Anyway, he sanctified this basket of dinarei to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. אזל נסיב בת, Azal nesiv bas,
so then the son went and he married בת גדיל כלילי דינאי
מלכא, bas gedil kelilei de-Yannai Malka,
a the daughter, a, a woman who wove the, the wreaths, you
know, of Yannai the King, okay, so she had a very nice
חשיבא chashiva job there in the palace. Her father, right? The, no,
the son. The son who had not been acting properly after the
father. The father did the weaving, not the daughter. Oh, oh, oh,
you're probably right, the daughter of the person who, ah, I see.
I was reading בת bas just as a woman who, but you're
probably right. Let me check the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it.
בת מי? Bas mi? Right, you're correct. You're right, you're right. The
daughter of a, thank you. The daughter of the person who made
the wreaths for the Yannai the king. Okay. אולידה דביתהו, Olida deveiteihu,
so his wife gave birth, you know, this, this young, this woman
he just married. זבן לה ביניתא. Zavan la binita.
He bought her a nice fish as a nice מזל טוב Mazal
Tov gift for having had a baby child, he went and he
bought her a fish. Okay. קרעה, Kar'ah, he opened up the fish,
okay, this son, this new husband. אשכח בה מרגליתא, Ashkach bah margalita,
he found in it a pearl or a precious diamond. It's sort
of like the story about, you know, יוסף מוקיר שבת, Yosef Mokir
Shabbos, right? So anyway, so now so. This is Yosef ben Yoezer.
No, Yosef is the father.
Yeah, I don't know if I, I don't think it's the same
person but let's see. Same story though, the fish and the jewel
on Yom Kippur when the poor. That's what we're talking about, yeah,
yeah, okay. Anyway, so אשכח בה מרגליתא. ashkach bah margalita. אמרה ליה,
Amrah lei, so his wife said to him, לא תמטייה למלכא, la
tamteih le-malka,
don't go and try to sell it to the king for his
like crown or whatever, she knows stuff about the king's king, her
father works in the king's castle, okay. דשקלי ליה מינך בדמי קלילי,
de-shaklei lei minach bi-dmei kelilei,
they're going to lowball you and offer you a very low price
and once you're dealing with the king's officers, you're not really going
to be able to say no, apparently. So don't try to go
sell it to the king. זיל אמטייה לגבי גיזברי, Zil amteih legabei
gizbarei, go. Go bring it to the treasurer of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, they'll give you a fair price. Okay. ולא
תשיימי את *v'lo teshaymi at*. Now don't go ahead when you're discussing
it with the treasurer, suggest a price. How about X amount of
dollars? It's like what's that high school book they get everybody to
read? The Pearl or whatever? Right? You know what I'm talking about?
Milton Stein... Steinbeck, right, Stein... Steinbeck, there you go. Anyway, so it's
sort of like everybody lowballed him on the price he winds up
throwing the pearl back in. Anyway, that's not the end of this
story. Okay, go to the גזברי *gizbari* of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* and don't you suggest a price. Okay? אמירתו לגבוה
כמסירתו להדיוט *amireso l'gavo k'mesireso l'hedyot*. Then that'll be like giving a
gift to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. Your verbal statement
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* is like you gifted
it. Now what does it mean you gifted it? Like if you're
suggesting... now it means you might, like maybe it's worth a lot
more than you imagine. You'll suggest a price and then you'll be
committed to that amount. Now תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* asks why are you
committed to that amount? You didn't gift anything to הקדש hekdesh *Hekdesh*.
You're negotiating and you're suggesting a price. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* and
he actually gives evidence elsewhere that if you're selling something to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* and you say a price, you're
not locked into that price just because you verbally said the price.
So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says it doesn't create a binding sale just
because you said a price. You still have to do an act
of קנין *kinyan* like in this thing, okay? You haven't given the
money, you haven't done משיכה *meshicha*. What have you donated? You're just
negotiating. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says no, here's the problem. Let's say
the pearl is worth $100,000 and you don't know and you say
50,000. So now, or let me give a better example, so 40,000.
Okay? So what you've just implicitly done was donate $60,000 to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay? It's not that you're saying
40,000 is a commitment to sell and binds you to the 40,000.
Since it was worth 100,000 and you said 40, it's read as
a $60,000 donation to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. And then he'd
be like אונאה *ona'ah* like that and ביטול מקח *bitul mekach*? Well
that's a good question. That doesn't apply to the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash*. But that's a course of negotiation. Yeah, one of the rules
is never be the first, don't be the first one who says
a price because that anchors the discussion. Exactly, exactly. Meanwhile, it turns
out he's not such a bad person.
Well, we're going to see. Let's go see the story. Okay, anyway,
so first of all, she's just trying to get her husband to
get himself a good price. Okay? So don't you suggest a price.
You might have no idea what it's worth and you'll say too
low of a price and then you'll be like committed to it
to some degree. Okay? אלא לשיימי אינהו *ela l'shaymi inhu*. Let them
be the ones to first suggest a price. And רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
says also like they're honest, they're not going to lowball you, they'll
give you a good assessment. Okay. אמטייה *amtiyei*. So he brought it
to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. שמוה בתליסר אליפתא דדינרי *shamuha b'tlisar
alifta d'dinarei*.
They assessed the price at 13 baskets of gold dinars. Okay? As
opposed... remember, his father only gave away one basket. Okay. So... well,
didn't give one, gave it away to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
Okay. אמרו ליה *amru lei*. They said to him: שבע איכא שית
ליכא *sheva ika sheis leka*. We have with us seven to pay
you, but six we'll have to owe you. So... אמר amar, להו
*amar lehu*. He said back to them... by the way, the רשב"ם
Rashbam, *Rashbam* points out they wanted this jewel for the חושן *choshen*
of the כהן גדול *kohen gadol*. So okay, so... it had
a pearl? No, usually we translate מרגלית *margalite* as a pearl but
I don't think it means pearl in rabbinic. It means like a
jewel. Okay. So... שית ליכא *sheis leka*. אמר amar, להו *amar lehu*.
He said back to them: שבע הבו לי *sheva havu li*. Fine.
Give me the seven you have. שית *sheis*. The six that you
don't have: הרי מוקדשים לשמים *harei mukdashim l'shamayim*.
I'm giving it back to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. I'll sell
it only for seven. So it's a bit of a צדיק *tzaddik*
you think. Let's take a look where the story goes.
עמדו *amdu*. So they went and they wrote in their ledger, וכתבו
*v'chasvu*. יוסף בן יועזר Yosef ben Yoezer הכניס אחת *Yosef Ben Yoezer
hichnis achas*. Yosef Ben Yoezer, you know, brought into the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash* donated one basket of dinari, ובנו הכניס שש *uveno hichnis
sheish*, and his son outdid him, six baskets of dinari. Okay? That's
one version which seems to be that they're praising the son that
turned out to be a nice guy, a צדיק *tzaddik*. איכא דאמרי
*ika d'amri*. One minute, another version is what they wrote in is:
יוסף בן יועזר הכניס אחת *Yosef Ben Yoezer hichnis achas*. He gave
one basket. ובנו הוציא hotzi, שבע *uveno hotzi sheva*. And his son
took seven out. His son is not a good guy. Now why
not? So the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says because it was clear that
had they had all 13 baskets he would have taken all 13.
So he was only donating back to them what they didn't have
immediately there, but he was prepared to take from them the maximum
they were willing to give. So he's not such a great guy.
Let us take six and give at least one of the baskets
back, you know? Anyway, fine. Of even what they do have. He
emptied out all of their available funds. What? ויוציא חן *v'yotzi chen*?
Well right, but okay. He made us pay the full amount. He
could have donated the whole thing to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
Okay, anyway, so two versions of whether you interpret the son based
on this action as a good guy or not a good guy.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: מכדי קאמרי הכניס *mideka'amri hichnis*. Since
they say הכניס *hichnis*, he brought
in... מכלל דשפיר עביד, no, it shows you that the father did
a good thing. Now here's a good question: if the son is
a good guy in this story, does it show the father made
the right decision or the wrong decision? You could go the opposite,
I think our natural thing to say, oh look, his son was
a good guy, father made a wrong decision, he misjudged his son.
But the גמרא Gemara is going the other way. Look, it seems
like the father's decision had some impact. He cut his son off,
and that maybe made his son do תשובה teshuva and try to
improve his ways. So if the son turned out to be a
good guy, you see the father's decision to cut him off was
a good decision. Okay, that's not necessarily how we would have read
the story, I think. So the גמרא Gemara says: אדרבה, aderaba, say
the opposite. מדקאמרי, Mi deka amri, since it says הוציא, that he
took out, that he was, it's reading him that he was a
bad guy, מכלל דלאו שפיר עביד, miklal delav shappir avid, you see
his father's decision was no good. Now why not? The son's a
bad guy, the father cut him off. Because part of this is
that they're, you know, is that maybe the way the רשב"ם Rashbam
reads this is, is that if they're, if they're, if they're saying
something bad about the son, presumably they're saying something bad about the
father as well. So if they're saying, look, their son took, you
know, took all this money away from the בית המקדש, they're saying,
look, the father started by doing something wrong by taking the money
away from his son, and then the son continued in doing something
wrong by taking money away from the בית המקדש. Again, it's strange.
You would think that if the son turned out to be a
bad guy, it means that the father made a right decision. Anyway,
מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. me'ha leka lemishma mina. Either way the גמרא
Gemara says we don't have a clear conclusion from this case whether
the father did the right thing. It wasn't I say, of course
the point is also, it's bizarre. First of all, sometimes the גמרא
Gemara says, you know, you don't want to hurt your kids because
the grandkids might turn out okay. Is it really being fair to
future generations? That's not, you don't have any evidence of that consideration
factoring in here also. פשיטא, Peshita, if in one public case it
turned out to have been the right decision or the wrong decision,
that does not mean whether as a policy matter we would say
that we think that this is a right approach or not a
right approach. Okay, so it's it's quite strange. Although I do want
to say, by the way, about the version that he turned out
good and his father, you know, even though that that actually means
the father made the right decision, look, the father cut him off
and in the end he turned out good, must be his father
caused it. It just made me think recently I read this bizarre
story. I don't know if people are aware about this, that our
most recent constitutional amendment, and we have ones that's quite recent that
people probably are not aware of, was the result of a bad
grade that somebody received in college. So somebody did a college paper
on the Constitution and about amendments or whatever, and for their paper
they discovered that there was an amendment suggested like five years after
the founding of the United States, you know, about that basically that
Congress cannot award themselves a raise, it can't be effective during the
same term that they award themselves a raise. And it never got
enough states to ratify it. So, but it didn't have it didn't
have an expiration date. So it was just sitting there waiting to
be ratified. Of course, at the time it probably only needed two
more states, you know, now it would need it like 35 states.
So this guy wrote a paper about this, he got a C.
He was so angry that he got a C, he made it
his project to get this, you know, amendment ratified. And he kept
on writing all these letters to state legislators. Finally one state actually
ratified it, and then it got the ball rolling, and then it
got ratified. And this was like the most recent ratification. So you
see, so I'm reading this story and I'm saying what a stupid
teacher, she gave him a C, and the point of the story
was the opposite. Look, if she had given him a good grade,
it never would have happened.
Yes, professor actually retroactively changed the grade. Yeah, I know that. Okay,
so יוסף בן יועזר is really early in this period. Yeah, well,
there was still בית המקדש, right. And the other the other thing
was
they are not discussing the fact that his son has seven
baskets of דינרין, dinarin, maybe he doesn't need the money? Well, now
he doesn't, he had been cut off earlier. Anyway, okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so we don't have a
conclusion about that. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מאי הוי
עלה, mai hava ala,
so what was the conclusion? תא שמע, Ta shema, דאמר ליה שמואל
לרב יהודה, de'amar lei Shmuel le'Rav Yehuda, שמואל Shmuel said to רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שיננא, shinana, sharp one, sometimes that's a compliment, sometimes
it's like a whatever, an insult, anyway, לא תהוי בעבורי אחסנתא, lo
tehei be'avurei achsanta,
do not be part of a house that transfers over an inheritance,
ואפילו מברא בישא לברא טבא, va'afilu mibra bisha le'bra tava,
even from a bad son to a good son, even if you're
not completely disinheriting your sons, you're just reassigning the proportions, okay, or
maybe it means again totally cutting off a son, okay, וכל שכן
מברא לברתא, vechol sheken mibra le'varta,
certainly not take it away from the son and pass it on
to a daughter, which is completely taking it away from the proper
heirs. It's very funny because it echoes the word עבורי אחסנתא avurei
achsanta echoes the פסוק pasuk in the תורה Torah which is והעברתם
את נחלתו לבתו, ve'ha'avartem es nachalaso le'visso, right, when there are no
sons it's passed, it's taken away from what until then would have
been the rightful male heirs and given to the women. Anyway, but
here the point is that you know, don't don't be part of
a reassign. Now what does it mean don't be part of? Like,
I don't know, as a rabbi try to prevent people from doing
this, you should censure people who do this, and so on. But
anyway, it's clear that שמואל *Shmuel* at least was פסקנ'ינג *paskening* this
is not a good thing. And of course again what's quite interesting
is, so we create all these institutions to let somebody do it,
and then here we say it's not and this doesn't seem like
you're completely disinheriting. At least some of your sons are getting, and
does it mean that you're completely cutting off one? Again, maybe the
phrase אעבורי אחסנתא *avurei achsanta* suggests that you're completely cutting one son
off. So you can change the proportions, then you're working within what
we're trying to achieve, but don't go ahead and completely cut one
son off. Okay, but we didn't prevent it. A person is still
legally able to do it. We just showed our displeasure for it.
All right. So what? שמואל *Shmuel* yesterday was who also? שמואל *Shmuel*
yesterday made it possible to cut the wife off effectively. And here
he's trying to not prevent, you know, a son from being cut
off. Okay, but that's a good connection. Okay. וכל שכן דתנו רבנן
*vechol sheken d'tanu rabanan*. מעשה באדם אחד *ma'aseh b'adam echad* שלא היו
בניו נוהגים כשורה *shelo hayu banav nohaigim kashura*. There's a story with
one person whose kids were not acting correctly or sons. עמד וכתב
נכסיו ליונתן בן עוזיאל *amad vechatav nechasav l'yonatan ben uziel*. He wrote
his property to יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel *Yonatan ben Uziel*
because he wanted יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel *Yonatan ben Uziel*
to, I don't know, it was like giving it to, you know,
a good Torah scholar or we'll see there's other versions of this,
I mean not other version but other ways of explaining why he
gave it to him. מה עשה יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel
*ma asah yonatan ben uziel*? Now יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel
*Yonatan ben Uziel* wanted the son to actually get some of the
father's property. He did not approve of completely cutting a son off.
So what did he do? מכר שליש והקדיש שליש *machar shelish vehikdish
shelish*. He sold a third for his own purposes. He gave a
third to the בית המקדש *beit hamikdash*. והחזיר לבניו שליש *vehachzir l'banav
shelish*. And he gave a third back to the kids. And the
reason of the first two is presumably not because he wanted necessarily
to keep the money for himself, but as the story's going to
continue, as a way of demonstrating that he really treated it as
his own property. If he just would have immediately written a check
and gave it straight back to the kids, you would say you're
subverting what the father wanted, he gave it to you as a
gift. So it wasn't really yours then, you should, okay, well we'll
see about that. But here he's actually saying, "No, no, no, the
fact that I first spent it on myself and gave a donation
to the בית המקדש *beit hamikdash* shows that I do treat this
as my own money, that I'm not just acting," you know, and
there, so but once it's my own money and I've demonstrated that,
I'm also entitled to give a gift to whomever I want. Okay.
So, בא אליו שמאי Shammai במקלו ובתרמילו *ba elav shamai bemaklo uvetarmilo*.
So שמאי Shammai *Shamai* came to him with his staff and right
and his like, what's בתרמילו *vetarmilo* like a measuring rod? How'd they
translate תרמיל *tarmil*? Like a satchel? Right. Oh, oh, a
pouch, I'm sorry, the pouch, all right, sorry, sorry. The, right, right,
that's like the whole story with what's his name, רבי יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua*, right, right. Sorry, thank you. His stick and his pouch. I
was just thinking about it because שמאי Shammai *Shamai*'s stick is used
to sort of indicate שמאי Shammai *Shamai* like you know when he
beats out the prospective גר *ger* with the stick, it's like אמה
בנין *ama binyan*. Right, it's like right, that was the measuring rod.
Right. That shows like שמאי Shammai *Shamai*, you know, is very rigid,
everything's got to fit into the box. But here it just means
I guess that he traveled to him. Okay. אמר לו Amar lo,
*amar lo*, and שמאי Shammai *Shamai* basically said, "What are you doing?
You're subverting the will of the father." אמר לו Amar lo, שמאי
Shammai *amar lo shamai*, שמאי Shammai. *Shamai* said to him, right? No,
no. He said back to שמאי Shammai *Shamai*. It's clear that שמאי
*Shamai* just critiqued him. Oh, we don't have what שמאי *Shamai* said.
Correct. And he said back to him, שמאי *Shamai*, אם אתה יכול
להוציא את מה שמכרתי ומה שהקדשתי *im ata yachol l'hotzi et ma
shemacharti uma shehikdashti*, if you want are prepared to reverse my sale
and my הקדש hektesh, *hekdesh*, אתה יכול להוציא את מה שהחזרתי *ata
yachol l'hotzi et ma shehechizarti*. You can reverse what I gave to
the kids. Meaning the fact that I sold it and I sanctified
it shows that this is mine, and if you want to say
that by giving it back to the kids I'm subverting the will
of the father and ultimately the gift wasn't a gift because the
father made it never gave it to
me under, you know, if the father never would have wanted me
to have it, how I went back and given it to the
kids, if that's what you're going to פסקן *pasken* by giving it
back to the kids it's like I violated an implicit stipulation of
the father, fine, then you have to go ahead and be prepared
to reverse these other sales. And since obviously that would, you know,
be like too disruptive to reverse those other sales, so clearly then
what I, you know, I have treated it as my own and
I'm giving my own property to the kids and it's you know
and it is was valid. Let's finish the story. ואם לאו *veim
lav*, and if you're not prepared to reverse that, אי אתה יכול
להוציא מה שהחזרתי *ei ata yachol l'hotzi ma shehechizarti*, you can't. אמר
*amar*, so שמאי *Shamai* responded, הטיח עלי בן עוזיאל הטיח עלי בן
עוזיאל *hitiach alai ben uziel hitiach alai ben uziel*. You got me,
בן עוזיאל *Ben Uziel*. You got me, בן עוזיאל *Ben Uziel*. That's
like a little rough idiomatic expression like, touché, okay, you know, fine,
you got me. Now, מעיקרא מאי סבר *meikara mai savar*. Now, what
was he holding originally? Now who's the "he"? This we read this
in wait, I'm going to read this, we'll read this and then
I'll give you a different version of how this is read by
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* and by the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*. So, מאי סבר
*mai savar*, משום מעשה דבית חורון *mishum ma'aseh d'beit choron*. So why
was שמאי *Shamai* thinking, we'll read it this way, why was שמאי
*Shamai* thinking that it was not a good sale? Because of the
story of בית חורון Beit Choron? *Beit Choron*. Not a good gift.
Once he's going to give it back to the son, it shows
it wasn't a good gift. What made שמאי *Shamai* think that? But
if you do something that subverts the intent of the father you're
essentially showing... that it wasn't a good gift because of the story
of בית חורון. Beis Choron, What was the story of בית חורון?
Beis Choron Famous story. באחד שהיה אביו מודר הימנו הנאה. Be'echad shehaya
aviv mudar himenu hana'ah. Okay, somebody whose father he had was prevented
from getting any הנאה hana'ah from the son. Either the father took
an oath or the son took an oath and the father could
not get any הנאה hana'ah from the son. היה, hayah, now the
son was משיא בנו, masi bno, was marrying off his son, and
he wanted his father to attend. ואמר לחברו, Va'amar l'chaveiro, and he
said to his friend, Michael, he said, הרי חצר וסעודה נתונים לך
במתנה. harei chatzer use'udah netunim lach bematanah.
I've just rented out, you know, this beautiful hall,
and this all the catered food is here, this whole banquet hall
filled with food, ready for my wedding tomorrow morning. You know what
Michael, it's a מתנה matanah to you. Okay? By the way, we
have 300 guests coming tomorrow, but it's a מתנה matanah to you.
Okay? And therefore, my father, and therefore the father can come and
he's getting הנאה hana'ah from Michael's food and not from my food.
Okay, והם נתונים לך במתנה. veha'im netunim lach bematanah. ואין לפניך אלא
כדי שיבוא
אביו ויאכל וישתה, V'ein lifnecha ela kedei sheyavo aviv veyochal veyishteh, not
just implicitly, I'm explicitly, Michael. The real reason I'm giving it to
you is I want my father to come. Now the רשב"ם, Rashbam
there's another version of the story where I'm not that transparent, but
I just say it's given to you as a מתנה matanah and
I'd like my father to attend. Okay, but here you're really being
explicit, which is I'm only giving it to you so my father
can attend. עמנו בסעודה. imanu bas'udah. אמר לו, Amar lo,
so Michael here, who does not want to be used as a,
what do you call it, as a shill,
right? Or as a cutaway. Like what, I'm just going to play,
pretend that it's mine to help you invite your father? So he
says, אמר, אם שלי הן, im sheli hen, fine, if you really
mean that they're mine, הרי הם מוקדשים לשמים, harei hem mukdashin lashamayim,
I'll give it to the בית המקדש. By the way, the subtext
here is, if you want to cut out your son or you
want to prevent whatever, do something, you might as well give the
money to the בית המקדש, don't just give it to your next
door neighbor. Anyway, okay. אמר לו, so then he said back to
him, לא נתתי לך את שלי אלא שתקדישם לשמים? lo natati lach
es sheli ela shetikdesham lashamayim? I didn't give you my whole banquet
hall filled with food so you should give it as a donation
to the בית המקדש. אמר, this is the son, who's trying to
get his father invited. The son is the one marrying off another
child, a son. He's trying to get his father, the grandfather, invited
to the wedding. אמר לו, לא נתת לי את שלך, lo natata
li es shelcha,
you're right. You know why you gave it to me? אלא כדי
שאתה ואביך אוכלים ושותים, Ela kedei she'atah va'avicha ochlim veshotim, you and
your father would be able to eat and drink, and you'd be
able to invite your father, he would come, you guys would have
a grand old time, ומרצים זה לזה, umartim zeh lazeh, and you'd
be reconciling one to another. Doesn't sound like a bad thing. ויהי
עון תלוי בראשי, Veyehi avon talui beroshi, and it would be the
burden would be around my neck. Now, the עון. avon. Now, what
עון? avon? The parents are getting the father and the son are
getting together, you should be so thankful you're helping create שלום בית.
shalom bayis. But the עון avon is that you would be violating
the נדר, neder, okay, at least in Michael's mind. Now the question
is, would they really be violating the נדר? neder? I mean, it
might seem like Michael feels like he'd be violating the spirit of
the נדר, neder, you know, maybe אדרבה, adaraba, it's better to violate
the spirit of the נדר neder to do a technical workaround and
to be reconciled with one's parents. So the fact that you, the
fact that you are being so פרום, frum, you know, maybe you're
the bad guy here, like I found a good technical workaround to
achieve a larger greater good, and you want to be super מקפיד
makpid on the spirit of הלכות נדרים. hilchos nedarim. Okay, but anyway,
but that's what you've done. Now, who's right? So the גמרא Gemara
says, you know, would I be able to do this as a
workaround for הלכות נדרים, hilchos nedarim, to give it to somebody so
that and that they only own it to let me avoid the
consequences of הלכות נדרים? hilchos nedarim? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אמרו חכמים, ameru chachamim,
so the sages said, כל מתנה שאינה כדי שאם הקדישה מקודשת אינה
מתנה. kol matanah she'einah kedei she'im hikdishah mekudeshes einah matanah.
That this guy was right. If he did not if Michael did
not own it to the degree that he could actually be מקדיש
makdish it, then it means that he never really owned it. And
since he didn't really own it, and I really did not fully
give it to him as a מתנה, matanah, then if my father
were to come and eat at the סעודה, se'udah, he would be
eating my food, not Michael's food. So Michael was right, being מקדיש
makdish it, my inability to be מקדיש makdish was evidence that he
did not really own it. Now, we have two questions here. Number
one is, are we supposed to take this seriously? You can't own
something if you don't have the right to be מקדיש makdish it?
And number two, how is this relevant to our story? So first
of all, תוספות Tosafos, points out the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says, so if
I give you a מתנה, matanah, right, and I say, חנן, Chanan,
here is here's my beautiful new car, I like you so much,
it's a total מתנה, matanah, the one thing I ask I'm going
to stipulate is that על מנת שלא תקדיש, al mnat shelo tikdish,
that you don't give it you're not מקדיש makdish it. If you're
מקדיש makdish it, the whole מתנה matanah is בטל. batel. Okay? What
do you think? You think it's a good מתנה matanah or not?
Yes, it's totally a good מתנה. matanah. So what that he can't
be מקדיש makdish it? I can make any תנאי tnai I want.
Okay? I can say on the condition you don't give it to
your wife. It's also a good מתנה. matanah. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
says, and תוספות Tosafos reads our גמרא Gemara. this way, that this
the response was not meant literally, that somehow there's some condition that
a מתנה matanah only works if the person can be מקדיש. makdish.
What it means is that in this particular case, it was evidence
that the whole thing was a sham. Okay? That I really was
giving Michael no right to do anything for himself, that it was
implicit when I, especially if I said it's given to you so
you can invite my father to the meal, okay, so if Michael
has no ability to use it for himself or do anything other
than just do exactly what I want with it, so that gets
around this נדר neder thing, that's evidence that he doesn't really own
it. So the הקדש hektesh was just the particular example of that.
But what it really means is, is that if he doesn't have
any use, it's not one minute, it's not really his. So that's
number one about what this the end of this story means. Now,
how is this relevant to our story? Okay, so the way the
רשב״ם Rashbam says it's evidence relevant, is is that you know, is
that אביי Abaye is that שמאי originally thought that this guy didn't
have a right to to give it back to the kids because
that the father wouldn't have wanted him to give it back to
the kids, okay, which is sort of like the story of בית
חורון, Beis Choron, right, like you know, is the father wouldn't you
know, if you're in the בית חורון Beis Choron. but it's a
little different because in that case of בית חורון, Beis Choron it
was evidence that it was never good sale to be it was
never good מתנה matana to begin with. And at all, you know,
whereas here, it's like if you're choosing to give it back to
the kids, then it's no good. And it's also strange because it's
like it's like that doesn't mean that it's not really a gift,
that just means that's the gift with a with a stipulation. So
you know, so which is essentially what then, you know, יונתן בן
עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel responds back and he says no, it really
it's not like that story of בית חורון. Beis Choron. The story
of בית חורון Beis Choron the guy had no right to do
anything other than that, right, here, I did have a right to
use it in other ways and I actually did sell it and
I was מקדיש makdish it. So and once it's a good gift,
then I'm also entitled to what to give to the kids. But
it doesn't really explain it because let's say the father had explicitly
made a stipulation. If you ever give any of this back to
my kids, the מתנה matana is בטל. batel. Then it would have
been בטל. batel. So like it's not exactly clear what's bothering שמאי
and how יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel is responding back. So
תוספות Tosafot claims that this case actually was exactly the same as
this story, that the father the case with יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan
ben Uziel. was the same as בית חורון. Beis Choron, That the
father actually said to his kid who wasn't acting correctly, you can't
get any הנאה hana'ah from me. All my property is אסור בהנאה
assur behana'ah to you. Just almost fell and then the father had
regret. So what the father's sort of like regret was was that
he gave it to יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel
so that יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel would then give it
back to his son. He wanted so that's what like, you know,
and then so so יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel. knowing the
story of בית חורון rather than giving it all back to the
son which would have shown it never was a good gift, chooses
to use some of it on himself, demonstrating that it was a
good gift, which then entitles him to give the rest back. So
שמאי comes the way תוספות Tosafot tells the story, and שמאי doesn't
realize that he's sold some of it. שמאי thinks he's given it
all back to the kids and says, this is the story of
בית חורון, right, so obviously it wasn't a good gift if you're
giving it right, it shows it was all a sham because you
just turned around and gave it back. And he said no, I
already sold some, I already was מקדיש makdish some, so clearly it
wasn't a sham, etc. So why is he נצחתני, nitzachtani, which means
you bested me, it's just שמאי just didn't know. I know, I
know. So תוספות Tosafot makes it fit better by making the the
circumstances like almost identical to our case, but it doesn't it's not
clear that that's what's going on in our גמרא. Gemara It is
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ירושלמי Yerushalmi by the way has, if you look at
the bottom of תוספות, ירושלמי Yerushalmi has that as the story except
it reverses the roles of שמאי and יונתן בן עוזיאל. Yonasan ben
Uziel He says like six lines from the bottom וכן משמע בירושלמי
בנדרים דקאמר יונתן בן עוזיאל הדירו אביו מנכסיו. Vechein mashma ba-Yerushalmi be-Nedarim
d'ka'amar Yonasan ben Uziel hiddiro aviv minichasav.
It's almost like a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva story. יונתן בן עוזיאל
Yonasan ben Uziel had been his the father of יונתן בן עוזיאל
Yonatan ben Uziel sort of, you know, made all of the property
forbidden on his son, on יונתן בן עוזיאל. Yonatan ben Uziel, So
יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonatan ben Uziel. was the is the son. It's
not our case. It's a similar story but with the roles somewhat
you know, mixed you know, different. וכתבו לשמאי, Vechisvu le-Shammai, and gave
it to שמאי. מה עשה שמאי מכר מקצתם והקדיש מקצתם ונתן לו
את השאר. Mah asah Shammai machar miktzasam vehikdish miktzasam venasan lo es
hash'ar. אמר כל מי שיבוא ויערער על מתנה זו יוציא מיד הלקוחות
ומיד ההקדש ואחר כך יוציא מיד זה. Amar kol mi sheyavo veye'ar'er
al matana zo yotzi miyad halakuchos u-miyad hahekdesh ve-achar kach yotzi miyad
zeh. So had שמאי as the one that realized what to do
to get the property back, and had יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonatan ben
Uziel. being the one that was sort of being like disinherited. Okay,
but anyway, but that's the way תוספות reads the story that it's
more similar as showing that in order to make it a good
gift, to get around the נדר neder problem, you had you know,
he had to do this to demonstrate he wasn't just it wasn't
a sham, that he really did, you know, it really was his
property. Yes, and I'm understanding in in the case of the last
case with the father in the wedding,
why we say that if that it's not a good מתנה. matana.
I mean, it doesn't mean the only thing you can do is
invite the father, it means one of the things you have to
do, meaning let's say the guy has 300 guests And then he
says, "You know what? I don't like any of your guests. I'm
going to swap them all out. I'm going to invite your dad."
Would that not have been a good מתנה? matana? Correct, he would
have objected just as much. He said, "I didn't give it to
you so you can invite who you wanted. I just gave it
to you so you would invite my father." מן ההקדש Min ha-hektesh
is just an example. If he would have done the whole thing
and he said, "Thank you very much. I'm going to call it
all off, have the caterer give me back the deposit, and I'll
go buy myself that car I've had my eye on, right?" He
also would have objected. So it's not the הקדש, הקדש was just
what he happened to have done. It really means, "I would have
objected to anything you would have done other than just played along
with the game and invited my father." So that's the reason why
it's not a good מתנה. matana. Yes. So that, and that's why
in the יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonatan ben Uziel. when he actually does
something and that's valid, that entitles him now to do what he
wants with the rest. Yes. It's the first day of סוכות Sukkot
and I left my ארבעה מינים arba minim at home. That's exactly
what תוספות opens with. Yeah, מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matana al menat
lehachzir.
So that's why תוספות says that actually you can make a gift
that you can't be מקדיש. makdish. That this is not to be
read narrowly and literally. It's to be read when the whole thing
is a sham, it's not good. Because of the לשון lashon right,
בורמא, burma, מתנת בורמא. matnat burma.
Exactly. Okay, so now that we mentioned יונתן בן עוזיאל, Yonatan ben
Uziel, let's continue. Okay, with יונתן בן עוזיאל. Yonatan ben Uziel, תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. By the way, we never have a good reconciliation
whether you are, you know, whether you're supposed—I mean, it sounds like
we don't like people being disinherited. We try to find ways to
get the property back and so on. Okay, but what exactly are
the parameters and how does that work with the fact that we've
given a person so much power and mechanisms to reassign the inheritance
is not really being fully reconciled. Anyway, but here's a little story
about יונתן בן עוזיאל. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. שמונים תלמידים היו לו להלל הזקן. shmonim talmidim hayu
lo le-Hillel ha-zaken. Hillel had 80 students. Okay? שלושים מהן ראוים שתשרה
עליהן שכינה כמשה רבינו. shloshim mehen reu'im shetishre aleihen Shchina keMoshe Rabbeinu.
30 were at the level that the, that the שכינה Shchina would
rest on them like Moshe, except as the רשב"ם Rashbam and others
say, the generation wasn't ראוי לכך ra'uy lekach but they were ראוי
לכך. ra'uy lekach. The מהרש"א Maharsha also points out that there's another
גמרא Gemara that says Hillel was fit to have the שכינה Shchina
rest on him like משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. So this is a
way of saying that 30 of his students had achieved the level
of their teacher, had achieved the level of Hillel. Like האספקלריא המאירה,
ha-ispaklarya ha-me'ira, is that what it's saying? In theory, no. No, in
theory, that's not what happened, but in theory, if the דור dor
had been fit. שלושים מהן
ראוים שתעמוד להם חמה כיהושע בן נון, shloshim mehen reu'im sheta'amod lahem
chama keYehoshua bin Nun, were fit as that the sun should stand
for Yehoshua bin Nun. Of course, the רשב"ם Rashbam, says according to
the גמרא Gemara the sun also stood for Moshe, but anyway, another
30 were at the level of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun.
The מהרש"א Maharsha says Yehoshua was a תלמיד talmid of Moshe and
he quotes a גמרא Gemara that says, you know, Yehoshua—what was, how
was Yehoshua like Moshe? Moshe was like the sun and Yehoshua was
like the moon that reflected the sun. So he says that's what
it means תעמוד להם חמה ta'amod lahem chama is like the sun
is standing, but you're not the sun, the sun is standing opposite
you, you're reflecting the sun. So it's sort of playing off of
that theme. Okay, so 30 were fit students, they didn't get to
the level of Hillel, but they were like Yehoshua ויז-א-וי vis-a-vis Moshe.
בינונים, Beinonim, now the ones that were in the middle group, apparently
the Yehoshua group was the bottom third. The top third, the bottom
third, the 20 in the middle, not exactly third. What? Well,
the top group was
the שכינה. Shchina. No, no, no. Apparently, the bottom group is the
Yehoshua. The middle 20, בינונים, beinonim, גדול שבכולן יונתן בן עוזיאל. gadol
shebekulan Yonatan ben Uziel. So of those middle 20, the greatest of
the middle group was
יונתן בן עוזיאל. קטן שבכולן רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Katan shebekulan Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai. Gives you a sense of the range we're talking
about here. Okay, so אמרו עליו על רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, amru
alav al Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, you want to know who the
bottom of the lower of the middle group was? Let me tell
you about רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. שלא הניח
מקרא ומשנה גמרא הלכות והגדות דקדוקי תורה ודקדוקי סופרים וקלים וחמורים וגזרות
שוות ותקופות וגימטריאות ומשלות כובסים ומשלות שועלים שיחת שדים ושיחת דקלים ושיחת
מלאכי השרת. shelo hiniach mikra u-mishna gemara halachot ve-agadot dikdukei torah ve-dikdukei
sofrim ve-kalim ve-chamurim gezeirot shavot ve-tekufot ve-gimatriot ve-mishlot kovsim ve-mishlot shualim sichat
shedim ve-sichat dekalim ve-sichat malachei ha-shareit. He—none of this he left without
mastering all these areas. What are they? So obviously מקרא mikra and
משנה mishna are obvious. Like מקרא mikra is פסוקים, psukim, משנה mishna
is the sort of the, you know, the teachings of the rabbis
like the apodictic statement. גמרא Gemara is the, you know, it's not
necessarily the written ש"ס Shas which they didn't have, but it's the
discussions around the משנה. mishna. The הלכות halachot might be like the
רשב"ם Rashbam says הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom says that it means like the מדרשי הלכה, midreshei halacha, like
the ספרא Sifra and the מכילתא. Mechilta. הגדות Agadot is more aggadic,
what we call מדרש אגדה. midrash aggada. Okay, דקדוקי תורה ודקדוקי סופרים.
dikdukei torah ve-dikdukei sofrim. So דקדוקי תורה, dikdukei torah, the רשב"ם says,
you know, it could be like—what did he say it is? Like
extra letters or something.
וו דבזלח המנתני vav de-vazlach ha-matnai or דקדוקי סופרים dikdukei sofrim he
says are גזירות gezeirot of the
חכמים. chachamim. רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom has a nice read of דקדוקי
סופרים. dikdukei sofrim. He says that it means when the rabbis use
numbers as a way of pulling things together.
Like ארבעה אבות נזיקין, arba'ah avot nezikin, חמש עשרה נשים פוטרות צרותיהן.
chamesh esrei nashim potrot tzaroteihen. Okay,
that that's like
being מדקדק. medakdek. Okay, and then all of course the מדרשי, midrashei,
the ways of דרשין darshing פסוקים, pesukim, קל וחומר, kal vachomer, גזירה
שווה, gezeirah shavah, תקופות tekufot is knowing the seasons, you know, the
astronomy, גמטריאות. gematriot. We normally think גמטריאות gematriot is like the numerical
equivalent, but the רשבם says it more has to do with sort
of like reading the פסוקים pesukim as like acronyms, right, like, you
know, like reading the right, like the words of a the letters
of a word to indicate נוטריקון, notarikon, right, to indicate like some
type of multiple words. משלות כובסים mashlot kovsim like, you know, using
a משל, mashal, parables of, you know, even of
launderers or of foxes, שיחת שדים sichat sheidim the whisperings of the
of the of the demons in order that you can like, you
know, you know, take an oath and make them do your will.
Okay, שיחת דקלים sichat dekalim or of trees like like the רשבם,
you know, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom also says you could say some
incantation and the field will fill filled with trees. There's a גמרא
Gemara like that. The speech of the מלאכי השרת, malachei hasharet, the
דבר גדול ודבר קטן, davar gadol v'davar katan, big things and small
things. So what did we not talk about? דבר גדול, davar gadol,
what is דבר גדול? davar gadol? מעשה בראשית, ma'aseh bereishit, knowing the
secrets of creation. I'm sorry, מעשה מרכבה, ma'aseh merkavah, excuse me, the
secrets of the divine chariot. ודבר קטן, v'davar katan, what's דבר קטן?
davar katan? הויות דאביי ורבא, havayot d'Abaye v'Rava, all the unresolved questions
of אביי ורבא, Abaye v'Rava, they was already known way in advance
by יוחנן Yochanan by, you know, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai and he already knew all the answers to all of
that. By the way, there's a very famous use of this phrase
by the by רמבם, Rambam, because רמבם, Rambam, you know, opens his
משנה תורה Mishneh Torah with discussing like metaphysics, right, about, you know,
the existence of God and the heavenly angels and for רמבם, Rambam,
the whole goal of learning, you know, of keeping מצוות mitzvot and
even of like learning שס Shas and הלכה, halakhah, was in order
to lay the groundwork so you could devote your life to what
you're really supposed to do, which is study like philosophy and metaphysics
and contemplate God, which for רמבם Rambam is all included in the
phrase מעשה מרכבה. ma'aseh merkavah. He takes what is clearly a mystical
concept in the גמרא Gemara and makes it a rationalist philosophical concept
of theology and, you know, metaphysics. So רמבם Rambam says even though
this is the real goal of a person's like religious life, because
the rabbis called it it דבר גדול davar gadol compared to the
דבר קטן, davar katan, which is הויות דאביי ורבא, havayot d'Abaye v'Rava,
which is what all of learning שס Shas is, all of the,
you know, questions of אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava is the classic distillation
of the idea of what learning the תלמוד Talmud is, he says
nevertheless, a person shouldn't learn this other stuff, this metaphysics, until you've
filled your belly with meat and wine and with meat and bread.
And meat and bread is like learning all the הלכות halakhot and
learning all of שס, Shas, and after you're done, well he doesn't
say שס Shas because he probably figured you could just learn הלכה
halakhah by reading the משנה תורה. Mishneh Torah. But anyway, after you've
learned all the הלכה halakhah and you know how you're supposed to
live, then you can move on to the דבר גדול. davar gadol.
But it is a little bit funny, right, because the דבר קטן
davar katan is what all of classic learning is. הויות דאביי ורבא
havayot d'Abaye v'Rava in later rabbinic literature becomes the like the way
to say in a distilled form like you know what learning גמרא
Gemara. is about, like the שקלא וטריא, shakla v'tarya, the types of
questions of אביי ורבא. Abaye v'Rava. That's like you learn to eat
meat and bread and then later in life you become the no,
he actually says later in life you walk in the פרדס, pardes,
in the in the garden. He says no, you go out and
you take a walk to get off some of that you you're
loaded down. Okay, anyway, so הויות דאביי ורבא. havayot d'Abaye v'Rava. לקיים
מה שנאמר להנחיל אוהבי יש ואוצרותיהם אמלא. lekayem mah shene'emar lehan'chil ohavai
yesh v'otzroteihem amale. To bequeath, there's an interesting use of the word
bequeath. We're talking all about bequeathing property, and here those that actually
achieve the right greatness in life, you know, they are bequeathed with
true יש, yesh, with something true of, you know, of worthiness, which
is like, you know, knowledge of תורה. Torah. Okay, that same פסוק
pasuk is used at the end of the משנה Mishnah I think
in עוקצין, Uktsin, where it says that the צדיקים tzaddikim in the
end will get 310 worlds and it says להנחיל אוהבי יש. lehan'chil
ohavai yesh. So it's interesting, right, contrasting, this is like real wealth
as opposed to what we've been talking about now. And their, you
know, their treasure houses I will fill. וכי מאחר, v'chi me'achar, the
מהרשא Maharsha also says the purpose of this is to sort of
say like one minute, if this is what רבן יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai knew, who who could be above that? Right,
what's more than that? So that's like the פסוק pasuk of no,
no, no, ואוצרותיהם אמלא, v'otzroteihem amale, you know, you know, even though
this seems like it's covering everything, but the higher you are, the
deeper and broader your understanding even within all of these areas is.
Anyway, וכי מאחר דקטן שבכולם כן, v'chi me'achar d'katan shebekulam ken, if
that's the smallest of all of them, גדול שבכולם על אחת כמה
וכמה, gadol shebekulam al achat kama v'khama, just imagine. But this is
the middle, right, but this is only the middle group. Okay, אמרו
עליו amru alav on יונתן בן עוזיאל, if you want to get
a hint towards the greatness of יונתן בן עוזיאל, which is the
reason we brought this whole thing in here anyway, so they said
בשעה שיושב ועוסק בתורה, besha'ah sheyoshev v'osek baTorah, when he was learning
תורה, Torah, כל עוף שפורח עליו נשרף. kol of sheporei'ach alav nisraf.
Any bird that would fly above would be burned from the heat
of the תורה Torah he would generate because the angels would be
congregating above his head. Okay, so yes, and the קוצקר Kotsker has
an explanation of this, he says that all of his thoughts... Every
thought he was always every time he had a new thought another
thought would come and would destroy and go to a higher level
with another thought. Aha. So it's always constantly growing in his thought.
All right so that's what meaning that's why it makes him at
the higher level. Oh פורח poreiach it's נשרף. nisraf. It's like it's
one no I don't understand what does נשרף? nisraf? He says it
one thought is sort of like you know dissipated by the next
sort of thought that's even at the next higher level. Okay let's
move on. האומר
זה בני נאמן ha'omer zeh beni ne'eman this is what I thought
this is what I had jumped ahead with before. So before we
said that you can identify a בכור bechor from among your sons
but how about identifying who a son is? Okay somebody that nobody
assumes was a son and you say yeah this kid's my son.
Okay so you're believed. זה אחי אינו נאמן zeh achi eno ne'eman
if you say this is my brother. The father dies and ראובן
Reuven says about this kid oh this kid here לוי Levi yeah
he's our long-lost brother. Okay and שמעון Shimon says I don't know
what you're talking about that לוי Levi is no brother of mine
and it's not going to take away from the portion I'm getting
in dad's estate. So he is not נאמן ne'eman so ראובן Reuven
is not believed to say this is my brother and he's going
to get a portion of the estate. ויטול עמו בחלקו veyitol imo
bechelko he is believed for for his own part he is to
get. So imagine that let's ignore the idea of a בכור bechor
okay let's say that's whatever we're going to ignore בכור bechor for
now and let's say there are three fields okay so here's ראובן
Reuven and here's שמעון Shimon they each get a field and a
half.
And ראובן Reuven says לוי Levi is a brother okay and לוי
Levi should get one of the fields and שמעון Shimon says I
don't think he's a brother so I'm not giving him any of
my property. So ראובן Reuven has to keep by what he said
another
that you know he's bound by what he said so according to
ראובן Reuven לוי Levi one of
the half field that ראובן Reuven got belongs to לוי. Levi. He
doesn't have to give him half of everything he got right because
he's saying what I'm claiming is one half of what you know
this half field of mine and a half field of שמעון Shimon
that belongs to לוי. Levi. So if that's what you're claiming you're
at least bound by it in terms of your own portion. Yeah
but שמעון Shimon loses out with that. No שמעון Shimon says I
don't believe I don't accept that המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'ayah. But you marked a half. Right that's coming from that's
coming from שמעון's Shimon from ראובן's Reuven part of the estate. That's
coming from ראובן's Reuven. part of the estate. He says לוי's Levi
entitled to a half field from each of us but שמעון Shimon
says I'm not giving him mine I don't think he's a brother
you go prove he's a brother. So since you claimed that he
was a brother ראובן Reuven you gotta give him at least that
half. Why don't you just like the thing you marked as number
one why don't you just mark that and put that in half
why doesn't he get half of ראובן... It doesn't matter. He has
he has one and a half fields and a half field has
to go to לוי. Levi It doesn't matter where it's coming from.
Okay now ויטול עמו בחלקו veyitol imo bechelko
but he gets a portion of of ראובן's fields. מת יחזרו נכסים
למקומן
now if לוי Levi dies okay he got this half
field okay. לוי Levi died so that field goes back to ראובן.
They don't שמעון Shimon doesn't get to say oh now I've decided
he's my brother and now let's split that field. No if he
was your brother then you've been holding that half field all along
that belonged to him. You get that half field back and I'll
get this half field back. Okay but now the real question is
let's say לוי Levi made it big in the stock market okay
and now after he's dead I mean who cares about the lousy
half field this guy's got a hundred million dollars to his name
right? And now after he's dead שמעון's Shimon decided that that לוי
Levi actually is a brother. Oh yeah oh yeah you're right he
is my brother. נפלו לו נכסים ממקום אחר naflu lo nechasim mimakom
acher
so he got other wealth יירשו אחיו
עמו yirshu echav imo then שמעון Shimon actually doesn't sound fair but
שמעון Shimon actually now can say oh yeah I actually do do
realize you were right all along he was my brother. Okay and
now because now שמעון Shimon as a brother to לוי Levi why's
he allowed to do that? Why is he allowed to? I don't
know he could say before there wasn't sufficient evidence like you know
I don't know evidence came to light. Right so why is he
yeah I mean it is an interesting question but I guess ראובן
all along has been claiming that he's a brother so even according
to ראובן's claim even if שמעון Shimon said nothing even according to
ראובן's claim שמעון is entitled to half of what he gets from
לוי right? So even if שמעון doesn't change his tune right let's
say you know I don't know שמעון's out of the picture you
only have שמעון's kids or whatever it is. Based on ראובן's claim
if לוי dies they each get half. Now of this שמעון didn't
get anything because שמעון all along had been holding on to that
half but if לוי gets more money even just based on ראובן's
claim they're both equal heirs of לוי so you split it. So
you know obviously if you're in שמעון's position I mean if you
know that לוי is a brother it might be smart financially but
it's dishonest but if you don't know that לוי is a brother
then you should why concede it? You won't lose out you can
only gain. Okay so let's look at the גמרא. Gemara זה בני
נאמן למאי הלכתא zeh beni ne'eman lemai hilcheta
if somebody says. this is my son, he is believed. For what
halachic purpose is he believed? Well, it's obvious, but maybe not so,
because we're going to say something you might not have thought about.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל ליורשו. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel leyorsho.
Number one, he inherits from him, which is clearly what the context
was here. But number two, ולפטור אשתו מן היבום. ulifetur ishto min
hayibum. If the guy doesn't have any known sons and he says
"this is my son" and then he dies, his wife doesn't have
to do יבום yibum with a brother. Okay, he's believed. Now why
is he believed? We don't—we have a פסוק pasuk that you believe
him by the בכור, bechor, יכיר—בכור בן השנואה יכיר. yakir We do
not have a פסוק pasuk that you believe the father about a—that
somebody who's not known to be a son, to believe a guy
about a בכור bechor is somebody who's known to be a son,
your belief to say he's a בכור. bechor. But we don't have
a פסוק pasuk to say a father has special belief about who
is his son. Okay, not only that, you could imagine cases that
the father actually is wrong, like he thinks he's right, but you
know, he's misidentified, if he assumes that this is his son, it's
really some other man's son for all he knows, right? But anyway,
but we don't even have a פסוק pasuk that says that the
father's believed. So the
גמרא Gemara says—so the גמרא's Gemara now going to figure that out.
ליורשו פשיטא. Leyorsho peshita. Now it's obvious he's believed in terms of
inheriting. Why? So as רשב"ם and תוספות both point out, because he
could have given it to him as a מתנה, matanah, which means
but if that's why he's believed, there's a limit to that. Why—what
would be the case—what would not be included when he says "it's
my son"? If I'm only believed to say this guy's my son
because if I wanted to I could give him all my property
right now, so for what am I not believed? Property I'm getting
later. Any property I get after I make that claim would not
go to him, because I would not be able to give—right now
I can't give him property I'm going to have in the future.
So even within the claim that somebody's believed to say "this is
my son" and the son will be—will be an heir, that is
only relevant for property that is in the person's control right now.
Any property the person gets later, he would have to repeat on
his deathbed "this is my son" you know to cover any property
that he got after from the last time he said "this is
my son". So the reason he's believed to say "it's my son"
is because he could gift him the property right now, and therefore
it only works on property he has under his control right now.
But לפטור אשתו מן היבום איצטריכא ליה. lifetur ishto min hayibum itztricha
leh. Fine, that is obvious. But what isn't obvious is if he's
believed to get his wife off of יבום, yibum, because you might
think that's not in his control, right? I mean I could get
my brother killed, but what do I have in control to get
his wife off of יבום yibum if he doesn't have kids? So
it actually is in his control. Why is it in his control
other than knocking off his brother? He could have divorced his wife.
Okay. איצטריכא ליה. Itztricha leh. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא נמי
תנינא, ha nami tninah, but we talked about that. מי שאמר בשעת
מיתתו יש לי בנים נאמן. Mi she'amar besha'at misato yesh li banim
ne'eman. If somebody says at the moment of his death "I have
children"—not "this particular person's my children"—"I have children," he's believed and his
wife is exempt from יבום. yibum. יש לי אחים אינו נאמן. Yesh
li achim eino ne'eman. If he says that "I have
brothers" that you didn't know about and "my wife is obligated in
יבום," yibum, he's not believed. He's believed to say he has sons
to get his wife off יבום yibum or children, but not brothers
to obligate his wife. And now the גמרא Gemara just clarifies and
compares and we'll end with this.
התם דהא—where Hasam de-ha he's believed—הא נמי תנינא ha nami tninah means
why do we need our משנה Mishnah to tell me this? I've
already got this from this other source. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, there's a difference.
התם דלא מוחזק לן באח. Hasam dela muchzak lan be-ach. There, we
don't know that this guy has brothers and we don't know that
he has kids. So if he says "this is my brother"—so if
we don't know if he has brothers and we don't know if
he has kids, the default status of his wife is פטורה מיבום.
peturah mi-yibum. We don't know any brothers. So he's not believed to
say "I have brothers" to change his wife's status and to make
her—she's מוחזקת muchzeket exempt from יבום yibum just based on his say-so,
we can't create a burden, you know, say that his
death—force—now make his wife essentially an עגונה agunah or whatever and say,
you know, change her status and say she's חייבת ביבום. chayevet be-yibum.
But we can believe he has sons because that's consistent with our
default assumption anyway, meaning we already assume the wife does—isn't obligated in
יבום. yibum. So to say he has sons is just reaffirming from
a different perspective why his wife is exempt from יבום. yibum. So
to say he has sons
he's believed because it reaffirms that she's exempt. To say he has
brothers he's not believed because it goes against her current status of
being exempt from יבום. yibum. That's that case. התם דלא מוחזק לן
באח הכא אף על גב דמוחזק לן באח. Hasam dela muchzak lan
be-ach hacha af al gav de-muchzak lan be-ach. Even though we know
he's got a
brother and a wife is obligated in יבום, yibum, he's believed to
say "this is my son". Now why is that? We have—it's the
whole point is you can't change your wife's status based on what—our
presumption, you can't make her obligated if we presume she's exempt. Why
can you make her exempt if we presume she's obligated? Okay, so
the גמרא hasn't said that yet. So let's read that reason. אמר
רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מפני מה אמרו זה בני
נאמן. Amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mipnei mah amru
zeh beni ne'eman. Why did they say "this is my son" he's
believed to make his wife exempt from יבום yibum when we know
there are brothers? הואיל ובעל שאמר גירשתי את אשתי נאמן. Ho'il uva'al
she'amar gerashti et ishti ne'eman. husband says I divorced my wife, he
be believed. So wait, that's not right. That's a different point. So
אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef* מארי דאברהם *Mori d'Avraham*! So רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* said by the God of Abraham! Okay, תלי תניא
בדלא תניא *tali tanya bedelo tanya* you're linking something explicitly stated that
a person is believed to say this is my son and you're
saying oh, the reason he's believed to say it's my son is
because he's believed to say I divorced my wife. We've never said
anywhere that a person, a man, is believed to say I divorced
his wife. So how do you make something stated explicitly that we
haven't said that yet? אלא אי אמר הכי אמר *Ella i amar
hachi amar* here's what it means. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel* מפני מה אמרו *mipnei ma amru* why is
a man believed to say זה בני נאמן *ze beni ne'eman*? הואיל
ובידו לגרשה *Ho'il u'veyado lgareshah* because if I wanted to make my
wife exempt from יבום *Yibum*, I could do it some other way,
I could just divorce her. So because I have the ability to
make her exempt from יבום *Yibum*, I am believed to say that
I have a son that exempts her from יבום *Yibum*. Now, that's
not exactly a מיגו *migo* because there could be reasons I don't
want to divorce my wife right like, you know, first of all
you'd make her אסורה *asura* to a כהן *Kohen*, you know, maybe
whatever who knows maybe I'll still live for another few months or
whatever there could be reasons. So it's not like it's not like
if I wanted to lie I could just divorce my wife. That's
like a מיגו *migo*. Believe me that I'm saying the right thing
because if I wanted to lie maybe there's reasons I don't want
to divorce my wife. But what it means is a better way
of understanding it is since I have power over this area I
can control her יבום *Yibum* status if I have power regarding this
I'm believed in the area that I have control over. So it's
not the מיגו *migo* of obviously I'm telling the truth because I
could have done it another way. No you wouldn't have wanted to
divorce but if you have the power to affect her her יבום
*Yibum* status you're believed about it. Okay and therefore I know we're
just going over just one more minute just to finish this thought
okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel* מפני
מה אמרו *mipnei ma amru* זה בני נאמן *ze beni ne'eman*? הואיל
ובידו לגרשה *Ho'il u'veyado lgareshah*. Oh and and then that connects to
what we said before. אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef* השתא דאמרת
אמרינן הואיל ובעל שאמר גירשתי את אשתי *Hashta d'amart amrinan ho'il u'ba'al
she'amar gerashti et ishti*. Oh I'm sorry no we'll just end there.
So and the reason therefore and we'll pick up with this tomorrow
and that's the reason he's believed to say that he divorced his
wife as well. Since he could divorce her if he wanted to
that idea of בידו לגרשה *beyado lgareshah* is the reason for both
reasons. Because he's believed because he could divorce if he wants to
he's believed to say that he has sons and because he could
divorce if he wants to he's believed to say that he already
did divorce her. So and that's the so therefore they're both based
on בידו לגרשה *beyado lgareshah*. That's why he's believed to say זה
בני *ze beni* and that's why he's believed to say גירשתי את
אשתי *gerashti et ishti* but we'll pick up with the גירשתי את
אשתי *gerashti et ishti* part tomorrow. Okay we'll end.